Guide to the Papers of Simon Dubnow (1860-1941) 1589-1938, 1961 (bulk 1700-1900) RG 87
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
- Series III: Communalia, 1660-1912; 13 folders
  - Chronicles of Israel in the City of Mohilev Podolsk[III.17], undated (Folder 950, Item 73990-73991)
    excerpt from the Book of Statistics of the Province of Podolia, 2 pp.
  - Mohilev-on the-Dnieper[III.18], undated (Folder 950, Item 73992-74005)
    a) excerpts from Mohilev archival records
    excerpts from the book Belorussian Archive of Older Records, 1824, with annotations by S. Dubnow, Russian, 16 pp.
  - Mohilev-on the-Dnieper[III.18], 1884 (Folder 950, Item 73992-74005)
    b) excerpts from the description of the Mohilev Province, pp. 716 in a book, Russian, 4 pp.
  - Mohilev-on the-Dnieper[III.18], undated (Folder 950, Item 73992-74005)
    c) Azkarah for the martyrs of the year 1655, Mohilev Province, copied from a manuscript at the Shupol Synagogue by Shim'on Volkov, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Mstislavl Kehilla[III.19], 1818, undated (Folder 951, Item 74006-74015)
    excerpts from the pinkas of the Funeral Society for the year 5568 (1808), excerpts made by S. Dubnow
    a) story about Vashtsile, 4 Shevat, 5504 (1744), published in 5678 (1818) in He-avar, volume I
  - Mstislavl Kehilla[III.19], undated (Folder 951, Item 74006-74015)
    b) A Story of Miracles that Occurred in the year 5604 (1844) in Mstislavl, Hebrew, 5 pp.
  - Mstislavl Kehilla[III.19], undated (Folder 951, Item 74006-74015)
    c) a few chapters about the Mstislavl miracle of 1844 (The Purim of Mstislavl) sent by Yitzhak Malkin of Smolensk, with remarks by Dubnow, Hebrew, 10 pp.
  - Nesvizh-Snov[III.20], undated (Folder 952, Item 74016-74019)
    a) three halakhic decisions in the case between the kehillot of Nezvizh and Snov, copied by David Slutski of Snov, Hebrew, 4 pp., with remarks by Dubnow
  - Nesvizh-Snov[III.20], 1892 (Folder 952, Item 74016-74019)
    b) claims of the kehilla of Brisk (Brest Litovsk) in the dispute between Nesvizh and Snov, dated (5547) 1787, as told by David Slutski in a letter dated, 12 December, 1892
  - Nowogrodek/Novogrudok (Novaredok)[III.21], undated (Folder 952, Item 74020-74023)
    a) excerpts of statements by Boni Originis, 25 August 1739, about residential permits for Jews in Nowogrodek, Polish and Russian, copy of a copy
  - Nowogrodek/Novogrudok (Novaredok)[III.21], 1894 (Folder 952, Item 74020-74023)
    b) excerpt of pinkas mishnayot about the martyr R' Meyer, killed in Nowogrodek
    letter from Ya'akov Hirshovski, Vilna, 23 January
    text Hebrew, letter Russian, 4 pp.
  - Nowogrodek/Novogrudok (Novaredok)[III.21], 1893 (Folder 952, Item 74020-74023)
    c) clippings from Hamelitz, #116, about the martyrs of Velma, Sha’ul Aharon Rubinshteyn
  - Ostroh, Zaslav, Stepan and Olik, Volhynia Province[III.22], 1792 (Folder 953, Item 74024-74041)
    a) Megillat Tamuz, 5552, about the miracle in the war between Russia and Poland in Ostroh, 4 pp., Yiddish, calligraphy, 2 copies, Russian
  - Ostroh, Zaslav, Stepan and Olik, Volhynia Province[III.22], 1892 (Folder 953, Item 74024-74041)
    b) elegies for the martyrs of Zaslav, copy of an old manuscript, Hebrew, with an appendix by the copyist Mendelberg, 1 pp.
    printed in Hamelitz, 5652, #195-198, also used by Galant, in 1912
  - Ostroh, Zaslav, Stepan and Olik, Volhynia Province[III.22], 1795 (Folder 953, Item 74024-74041)
    c) two letters from Mendelberg of Ostroh, dated Wednesday, week of zot ha-brakhah, about Zaslav, Stepan and Olik, in Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - Ostroh, Zaslav, Stepan and Olik, Volhynia Province[III.22], undated (Folder 953, Item 74024-74041)
    d) Megillat Stepan (The Scroll of Stepan) about the libel cast on R’ Yoel of Lutsk, Hebrew, 7 pp.
    information about Stepan and Olik, by Mendelberg, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Ostroh, Zaslav, Stepan and Olik, Volhynia Province[III.22], 1740 (Folder 953, Item 74024-74041)
    e) inscription on the gravestone of R' Shmuel Eliezer son of Yehudah (Maharsha) in Ostroh, 7 Heshvan, 5501, and his family, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Ostropol[III.23], 1895 (Folder 954, Item 74042-74043)
    stories about the burial of R’ Shimshon of Ostropol, in a letter by Moshe Spiglbord, 11 June, from Ostropol
  - Pinczow[III.24], 1894 (Folder 954, Item 74044-74060)
    a) Siddur Pintshev, copies of an old prayer book, manuscript from the Pintshev Beit Midrash, dated 5375 (1614), copies made by S. Dubnow, July 1894, 6 pp. Hebrew
  - Pinczow[III.24], 1894 (Folder 954, Item 74044-74060)
    b) letter from the rabbi of Herzog, R’ Yosef Bera, about the Pintshev Siddur, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Pinczow[III.24], 1894 (Folder 954, Item 74044-74060)
    c) two El mole rakhamims for the martyrs of Pintshev, copies by Yitzhak Meyer Levinshteyn of Koszyce
  - Plock[also III.24], undated (Folder 954, Item 74044-74060)
    a) two documents from years 1754 and 1792, about the persecutions and murder of the Plock Jewish elders by the town administration, Polish translations of Hebrew texts excerpted from the synagogue records, 3 pp.
  - Plock[III.24], 1894 (Folder 954, Item 74044-74060)
    b) letter from Israel Nozyca, 14 February, about the persecutions and murder of the Plock Jewish elders by the town administration
  - Pohrebishtche[III.25], 1894 (Folder 955, Item 74061-74066)
    miscellaneous stories about the town in a letter by Fishl Guttman to Dubnow, Hebrew, 6 pp.
  - Poznan (Poyzn, Posen)[III.26], 1865 (Folder 955, Item 74067-74083)
    a) chronicles of the City of Poznan about the persecutions in 1704, 1717, 1736, drawn from Kuntres (notebook, logbook) of Poznan, referred to by Perles in the History of the Jews of Posen (German), Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Poznan (Poyzn, Posen)[III.26], 1891 (Folder 955, Item 74067-74083)
    b) elegy for the Fire of Posen, from the book P'nei Yitzhak by R’Yitzhak Khayes, Krakow, 5351, 6 pp., Hebrew
  - Poznan (Poyzn, Posen)[III.26], 1796 (Folder 955, Item 74067-74083)
    c) penitential recitations for the 5th of Av, the persecutions of 5476 (1706-1707) taken from Kuntres, Dyhernfurth, 5556, 8 pp, Hebrew
  - Poznan (Poyzn, Posen)[III.26], 1733 (Folder 955, Item 74067-74083)
    d) Even ha-shoham the Onyx Stone, excerpts from the book of responsa, by Eliyakum Getz, Dyhernfurth 5493, regarding the persecutions of 5460-5478 (1700-1718), prepared by Ya'akov Shapiro of Mezrich, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Poznan (Poyzn, Posen)[III.26], 1803 (Folder 955, Item 74067-74083)
    e) excerpts from "Ma'aseh ha-shem" (God’s Deeds), Roedelheim 5513 (1753) about the false accusation in Posen, Shevat 5563, 6 pp., Hebrew
    [III.27 not used]
  - Pruzany[III.28], 1895 (Folder 955, Item 74084-74087)
    excerpt from the community pinkas of Pruzany, 5568-5574 (1808-1814) and other data in a letter from Moshe-Nissan Yanovski, dated first day of hol ha-moed Sukkot, 5656, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Rasin (Raseiniai)[III.29], 1897 (Folder 955, Item 74088-74090)
    story about Pan Stolnik and the repressions of Jews in Rasin and other data, in a letter from the Vilna Rabbi, R’ Finfer, dated 15 Av, 5657, 3 pp., Hebrew
  - Ruzhana[III.30], 1660 (Folder 956, Item 74091-74120)
    a) selihot (penitential/mourning) prayers for the martyrs of Ruzhana, 5420, copies by Dr. Yosef Chazanovitsh from a general ledger in Ruzhana
  - Ruzhana[III.30], 1660 (Folder 956, Item 74091-74120)
    b) Da'at kedoshim al harugei Ruzhana 5420 (1660) ve-yihusam, recognizing the victims of Ruzhana killed in 1640 and their lineage, Hebrew, 39 pp., pp. 19, 20 missing
  - Ruzhana[III.30], undated (Folder 956, Item 74091-74120)
    c) selihot for the martyrs of Ruzhana, written by R’ Shim'on Khozok, transcribed from a manuscript owned by R’ Eliyahu Yafe in Ruzhana, with remarks by S. Dubnow, Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Ruzhana[III.30], 1893 (Folder 956, Item 74091-74120)
    d) copy of the 5635 (1875) monument for the Ruzhana martyrs of the blood libel of 5420 (1600), R’ Yisrael and R’ Tuviah, plus some notes about the blood libel, in a letter to Dubnow dated 12 Tishrei 5653, sent by Aharon Moshe Mazursky, Ruzhana, with remarks appended by Dubnow, Hebrew and Russian, 4 pp.
  - Slonim[III.31], 1764 (Folder 957, Item 74121-74122)
    copy of the pinkas of the Bikur Holim Society, transcribed by R’ Yitzhak Shamash in Slonim, Hebrew, 2 pp., also about the pogrom of 5524
  - Slutsk[III.32], 1894 (Folder 957, Item 74123)
    copy of the pinkas of the hevra kadisha of Slutsk, starting in 5438 (1678), Hebrew, 1 pp.
  - Ushitsa Trial[III.33], 1838-1840 (Folder 957, Item 74124-74135)
    regarding attacks by local Jews against Jewish informers
    a) proceedings of trial, 16 pp., Russian, with Dubnow’s remarks, copy, first 2 pp. are missing
  - Ushitsa Trial[III.33], undated (Folder 957, Item 74124-74135)
    b) report of the trial in a letter account of the Litnivetser Mayse, written on stationery of Sh. A. Hornshteyn, Odessa, Russian, 7 pp.
    printed in the book Perezhitoe, volume I
  - Lublin[III.34], 1902 (Folder 957, Item 74136-74139)
    a) lists of Prayers about the Cruelty, translated from a manuscript from Lublin including about the history of Jews in Lublin
    copy by Dubnow from a copy by Sh. Nisnboym, Adar 5662, Hebrew, 3 pp.
  - Lublin[III.34], 1902 (Folder 957, Item 74136-74139)
    b) letters from the kehilla of Lublin dated 1709 (5469), also from 2 Av, 5469 to R’ Aharon Avraham Ber, shtadlan, (intercessor and advocate for the Jewish community) in Oyrikh, regarding help, especially in this difficult time
    with great and lavish recommendations, copy to Dubnow, according to a copy sent by Dr. Chazanovitsh, Hebrew, 1 pp.
- Series IV: Pogroms, 1881-1923; 19 folders
  The materials in this series were gathered mostly during Dubnow’s last years in Russia, between 1919 and 1922. Dubnow was then involved in editing the documentary volumes on anti-Jewish pogroms in Russia and he spent considerable time poring over the newly available records of the former imperial archives. In this series, there are reports by government officials and other information about pogroms in the modern era, including those of 1881, 1903, 1905, and 1906. In addition, there are memoranda on the situation of Jews in Russia that were submitted to the Pahlen Commission in 1884, including one written by Dubnow.
  - List of files, undated (Folder 958, Item 74140-74141)
    (incomplete)
  - Reports about pogroms[IV.1], 1881 (Folder 959, Item 74142-74217)
    a) information from police precincts, from German newspapers and from miscellaneous reports, April-May 1881, largely in Russian, 68 pp.
    Reel 75
  - Reports about pogroms[IV.1], 1881-1882 (Folder 959, Item 74142-74217)
    b) reports about pogrom agitation and orders, related to the trial of the pogrom perpetrators, May 1881- January 1882, Russian, printed copy, 17 pp.
  - Report by Count Kutaisov[IV.2], undated (Folder 960, Item 74218-74319)
    a) about the pogroms of June 1881 in Bessarabia, Poltava Province, and Kiev Province
    report by Jews of Yelizavetgrad about the pogroms in Southern Russia, in Kherson Province, printed copies, Russian, 99 pp.
  - Report by Count Kutaisov[IV.2], 1923 (Folder 960, Item 74218-74319)
    b) addendum to Kutaisov report, 3 pp., Russian
  - Report by Prince Shakhovsky[IV.3], 1881-1882 (Folder 961, Item 74320-74326)
    about the pogrom in Chernigov Province, August 1881-January 1882, Russian, 7 pp.
  - Pogrom in 1881[IV.4] (Folder 961, Item 74327-74334)
    correspondence about agitation between the police gendarmerie, typed copies, Russian, 8 pp.
  - Pogroms of 1882[IV.5] (Folder 962, Item 74335-74381)
    documents about the pogroms in Podolia, pp. 1-5; Kherson, pp. 6-14; Chernigov, pp. 15-16; Bessarabia, pp. 17-18; Kiev, pp. 19; Yekaterinoslav, pp. 20; Poland, pp. 21-23; general letters about pogroms, pp. 24-26; emigration and groups, pp. 27-29; addenda, pp. 30-46
  - Odessa pogroms of 1900[IV.6], 1900-1902 (Folder 963, Item 74382-74397)
    pogrom in Konstantinovka, Lithuania, 1900
    Czestochowa pogrom of 1902
    the situation in Mohilev, 1902
    copies, 16 pp., Russian
  - Dubossary blood libel[IV.7], 1903 (Folder 964, Item 74398-74426)
    copy, Russian, 29 pp.
  - Kishinev pogrom[IV.8], 1903 (Folder 965, Item 74427-74486)
    copy, typescript, Russian, 60 pp.
  - Homel pogrom and Vitebsk confrontation[IV.9], 1903 (Folder 966, Item 74487-74497)
    copy, typescript, Russian, 11 pp.
  - Pogroms in 1904[IV.10] (Folder 966, Item 74498-74501)
    pogroms in Vitebsk and Smola, copies in typescript, 8 pp. folio, Russian
  - Pogroms in 1905[IV.11] (Folder 966, Item 74502-74518)
    pogroms in Zhitomir, Polotsk, Vitebsk, Melitopol, Brest, and Grodno, copies and typescripts, 17 pp., Russian
  - Pogroms in 1905[IV.12] (Folder 967, Item 74519-74582)
    pogroms in Minsk, Saratov, Vitebsk, Skidele, Vilna, Yekaterinoslav, Kishinev, Bessarabia in general, Saratov, Bialystok, Grodno, Kiev, Berdichev, Uman, and Rostov
    various circulars prepared by the police department in 1905, about the pogroms, copies, 66 pp., Russian
  - Bialystok pogrom[IV.13], 1906 (Folder 968, Item 74583-74591)
    copies, typescript, 9 pp., Russian
  - Bialystok pogroms[IV.14], 1905-1906 (Folder 968, Item 74592-74604)
    copies, typescript, 13 pp., Russian
  - Homel pogrom[IV.15], 1906 (Folder 968, Item 74605-74619)
    copies, typescript. 15 pp., Russian
  - Miscellaneous pogroms, 1903-1907[IV.16] (Folder 969, Item 74620-74624)
    a) Zvenigorodok, Kishinev, regarding Jewish recruits, Bialystok Pogrom, Siedlce pogrom, the situation in Podolia and Volhynia, copies, typescript, 4 pp., Russian
  - Miscellaneous pogroms, 1903-1907[IV.16], 1905 (Folder 969, Item 74620-74624)
    b) telegram to the Ministry of Justice about the pogrom in Melitopol, copy, typescript, 1 pp., Russian
  - Court case between residents of Birzai and Count Tyszkiewicz[IV.17], 1892 (Folder 970, Item 74625-74643)
    printed copy of decisions of the suit and signature of Tyszkiewicz attorney, Bernard Andreevich Fridman, 19 pp., Russian
  - Project of Minister of Interior V.K. Plehve[IV.18], 1904 (Folder 971, Item 74644-74671)
    regarding changes in legislation concerning Russian Jews, copy, typescript, 54 pp., Russian
  - Prince N. Golitzin’s book[IV.19], 1886 (Folder 972, Item 74672-74682)
    excerpt from Istoriia Russkogo Zakonodatel’stva o Evreiakh (The History of Russian Legislation Regarding Jews), volume I, (1649-1825), St. Petersburg, Russian, 14 pp.
  - Report on the question of Jews’ education[IV.20], 1886 (Folder 973, Item 74683-74863)
    by Georgeevskii, A., to the Pahlen Commission, printed, 314 pp., notes by Dubnow
    Reel 75-76
  - Review of the Laws Regarding Jews in Russia Today[IV.21], 1883 (Folder 974, Item 74864-74917)
    report by Margolis for the Pahlen Commission, Russian
    Reel 76
  - The Jewish Question and the Pogroms of 1881-1882[IV.22], undated (Folder 975, Item 74918-75052)
    report for the Pahlen Commission, 248 pp., Russian
  - Megillat Shabtai[IV.23], 1893, undated (Folder 976, Item 75053-75057)
    chronicles of the pogrom in the town of Bobovne in the year 5589 (1829), Hebrew, copied from a manuscript by R’ Aharon Yehoshua Tov be-ha-rav Shabtai, 4 pp., undated
    clipping from Hamelitz, #37, Ir ha-damim (The City of Blood), by Y. N. Goldberg
- Series V: Miscellaneous, 1760-1921; 15 folders
  This series contains a variety of historical documents that often overlap with the above listed materials. Worth mentioning is a collection of family documents of the Dubnow family, including personal documents of Ben-Tsion Dubnow, Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, who was a teacher in Mstislavl.
  - General Privilegium und Reglement[V.1], 1912 (Folder 977, Item 75058-75085)
    issued by Friedrich II in 1750 for the Jews of Prussia, copy, German
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1782 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    a) contract with Michal Parczewski regarding building a house on his parcel of land, Polish, 2 pp., original
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1799 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    b) contract, 17 April, regarding leasing a parcel of land in Mstislavl, Polish, 1 pp., original
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1825 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    c) script of an administrative decision in connection with a request by Velki (Volf?) Dubnow, son of Ben-Tsion, 21 August, regarding a house
    VD was a resident of Mstislavl
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1831 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    d) decision about a rental by Velki (Volf?) Dubnow, 29 September, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1839 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    e) will and testament of Victor (Avigdor), son of Volf Dubnow, 24 August, Russian, 4 pp.
    pagination starts with pp. 3, first and second sheets missing
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1839 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    f) fragment of will, Hebrew, written in Avigdor (Victor) Dubnow’s hand
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1844 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    g) certificate issued to Ben-Tsion Dubnow by the Mstislavl magistrate concerning his father’s (Avigdor’s) will, Russian, 22 January, 4 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], undated (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    h) blank check, signed by Avigdor Dubnow, Russian
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1885 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    i) power of attorney for handling matters in the name of the Christian and Jewish merchants in Mstislavl and requesting permits for brick houses, April, draft, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1838 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    j) contract between Avigdor (Victor) Dubnow and Yisrael-Isser, son of R’ Mordekhai Khazanov, 23 August, presented to the Mstislavl police, with signatures and approvals, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1838 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    k) contract with the signatures of Avigdor, son of Rabbi Volf Dubnow, Yisrael-Isser, son of R’ Mordekhai Khazanov, and others, Hebrew, 2 pp., 6 Elul 5598, Mstislavl
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1856-1858 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    l) five documents concerning the Jewish School in Mstislavl
    (1) to Ben-Tsion Dubnow regarding using his home as a school building, December 3, 1856
    (2) to Ben-Tsion Dubnow regarding housing the school in his home, 31 June, 1856
    (3) outlines Ben-Tsion Dubnow's role as honorary chairman of the school, 28 January, 1857
    (4) request to Ben-Tsion Dubnow to send his annual contribution to the school, 23 January, 1858
    (5) receipt for that money
    these documents are written on the stationery of the directorship of the Mstislavl school, 12 February, 1858, Russian
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1856 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    m) ledger of Ben-Tsion Dubnow as honorary chairman of the Mstislavl Jewish school for the year 1856, 2 pp., Russian
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1820 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    n) letter from Avigdor Dubnow to his brother Moshe regarding his rights to the house in Mstislavl, November, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1843 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    o) certified notice from Hillel Rapoport to Ya'akov, son of David Yakubson, 9 December, regarding decisions of the court in Vilna concerning a house, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1865 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    p) (1) request from Ben-Tsion, son of Avigdor Dubnow, to borrow money to rebuild his house that had burned down, on the grounds of the royal decree of 1859
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1863 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    p) (2) request from Ben-Tsion, son of Avigdor Dubnow, to the head of the Mohilev Province, 31 October, related to the fires of 1858 and 1863 in Mstislavl
    written in Mohilev, where Dubnow was temporarily residing, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1861 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    q) (1) request from Nahman, son of Mordekhai Kahanov of Mstislavl, regarding a debt of 150 rubles, September
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1858 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    q) (2) loan document from Leib, son of Avrom Kahanov, dated 14 July, regarding the obligation of Nahman, son of Mordekhai Kahanov, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1869 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    r) certification to Ben-Tsion, son of Avigdor Dubnow, December, granting permission to live anywhere in Russia, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1843 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    s) contract regarding residence in the house of Ben-Tsion Dubnow, between himself and Leib Lipshits, dated 1 May, originals with signatures of Dubnow, Lipshits and witnesses, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], undated (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    t) mortgage document
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1851 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    u) contract drawn by the Mstislavl community about installing a new shoykhet, Shneyer Yitskhok, son of Shmuel Halevy, with signatures of a large number of town balebatim (householders), among them Ben-Tsion Dubnow, 2 pp., Hebrew
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1856 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    v) petition for help for Pesach from the community of Mstislavl to Countess Saltykova, as their protector, in connection with the banishment of 1843, 3 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1860 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    w) response to a request to the Mohilev governor from the Mstislavl citizens and merchants’ association, 4 pp.
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], undated (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    x) listing of ma'ot hittim donations in Mstislavl with many names of local balebatim (householders), Hebrew
  - Family papers of Simon Dubnow’s grandfather, Ben-Tsion Dubnow[V.2], 1906 (Folder 978, Item 75086-75159)
    y) beit din of Mstislavl, judgement dated Monday, 26 Sivan, 5666, regarding house belonging to David, son of Meyer Frumkin and his sister-in-law, shows signatures of beit din and witnesses, Hebrew, 2p.
  - Decisions of Lithuanian assessors in the trial of the Vilna Kahal of 1767[V.3], 1798-1807 (Folder 979, Item 75160-75182)
    excerpted from the municipal books of Vilna county, 1799, Polish, 8 pp. numbered 216-220, with signature
    Russian translation of the document, 6 pp. numbered 210-215
    also copy of the Russian translation written partly by Dubnow himself, undated
    another Polish copy of the above excerpt, made on July 12, 1807, pp. 196-203
  - Lists[V.4], 1760 (Folder 980, Item 75183-75206)
    copied and transcribed in a notebook, 40 pp., Russian
    a) translation from a Polish book by the priest Tikulski, Zlosc zydowska (Jewish fury), published in Lemberg (Lvov), pp. 1-7, 15-36
  - Lists[V.4], 1794 (Folder 980, Item 75183-75206)
    b) excerpt from the book Talmud Stories, Polish, pp. 8
  - Lists[V.4], undated (Folder 980, Item 75183-75206)
    c) excerpt from Jewish seforim by the priest Pazdzierski, translated from the Polish into Russian